<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Heritrix developer documentation</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>$Date: 2007-03-23 16:06:32 +0000 (Fri, 23 Mar 2007) $</date>

    <authorgroup>
      <corpauthor>Internet Archive</corpauthor>

      <editor>
        <firstname>John Erik</firstname>

        <surname>Halse</surname>
      </editor>

      <author>
        <firstname>Gordon</firstname>

        <surname>Mohr</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Kristinn</firstname>

        <surname>Sigurđsson</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Michael</firstname>

        <surname>Stack</surname>
      </author>
      
      <author>
        <firstname>Paul</firstname>
        <surname>Jack</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This manual is intended to be a starting point for users and
    contributors who wants to learn about the internals of the Heritrix web
    crawler and possibly write additions or contribute to the core of the
    software. The <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/index.html">javadoc API
    documentation</ulink> is supposed to be the main developer documentation,
    but this document should help you get started and guide you to the
    interesting parts of the Javadoc documentation.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="building">
    <title>Obtaining and building Heritrix</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Obtaining Heritrix</title>

      <para>Heritrix can be obtained as packaged binary or source downloaded
      from the crawler <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/archive-crawler">sourceforge home
      page</ulink>, or via checkout from archive-crawler.svn.sourceforge.net. See the
      crawler <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/svn/?group_id=73833">sourceforge svn
      page</ulink> for how to fetch from subversion. The <literal>Module Name</literal>
      name to use checking out heritrix is
      <literal>ArchiveOpenCrawler</literal>, the name Heritrix had before it
      was called Heritrix.
      </para>
      <note><para>Note, anonymous access does not
      give you the current HEAD but a snapshot that can some times be up to 24
      hours behind HEAD.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The packaged binary is named heritrix-?.?.?.tar.gz
      (or heritrix-?.?.?.zip) and the packaged source is named
      heritrix-?.?.?-src.tar.gz (or heritrix-?.?.?-src.zip) where ?.?.? is the
      heritrix release version.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Building Heritrix</title>

      <para>You can build Heritrix from source using Maven. Heritrix build has
      been tested against maven-1.0.2. Do not use Maven 2.x to build Heritrix.  See <ulink
      url="http://maven.apache.org">maven.apache.org</ulink> for how to obtain
      the binary and setup of your maven environment.</para>

      <para>In addition to the base maven build, if you want to generate the
      docbook user and developer manuals, you will need to add the
      maven sdocbook plugin which can be found at
      <ulink
      url="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/maven-sdocbook-plugin/downloads.html">this page</ulink> (If the sdocbook plugin is not present, the build
      skips the docbook manual generation).
      Be careful. Do not confuse the 'sdocbook' plugin with the similarly
      named 'docbook' plugin. This latter converts docbook to xdocs where
      what's wanted is the former, convert docbook xml to html. This
      'sdocbook' plugin is used to generate the user
	and developer documentation.</para> 

	<para>Download the plugin jar -- currently, as of this writing, its
    maven-sdocbook-plugin-1.4.1.jar --
    and put it into your maven repository plugins directory, usually      
               at <literal>${MAVEN_HOME}/plugins/</literal> (in earlier
               versions of maven, pre 1.0.2, plugins are at
               <literal>${HOME}/.maven/plugins/</literal>).
               </para>

	<para>The sdocbook plugin has a dependency on the <ulink
      url="http://java.sun.com/products/jimi/">jimi jar from sun</ulink> which
      you will have to manually pull down and place into your maven
      respository (Its got a sun license you must
               accept so maven cannot autodownload).
               Download the jimi package and unzip it.  Rename the
               file named <literal>JimiProClasses.zip</literal>
               as <literal>jimi-1.0.jar</literal> and put it into
               your maven jars repository (Usually
               <literal>.maven/repository/jimi/jars</literal>. You
               may have to create the later directories manually).
		Maven will be looking for a jar named 
                jimi-1.0.jar.  Thats why you have to rename the
		jimi class zip (jars are effectively zips).
               </para>

       <note>
      <para>It may be necessary to alter the <literal>sdocbook-plugin</literal>
       default configuration.  By default, sdocbook will download the latest 
       version of <literal>docbook-xsl</literal>.  However, sdocbook hardcodes 
       a specific version number for <literal>docbook-xsl</literal> in its
       <literal>plugin.properties</literal> file.  If you get an error like
       "Error while expanding ~/.maven/repository/docbook/zips/docbook-xsl-1.66.1.zip",
       then you will have to manually edit sdocbook's properties.  First determine
       the version of <literal>docbook-xsl</literal> that you have -- it's in 
       <literal>~/.maven/repository/docbook/zips</literal>.  Once you have the
       version number, edit <literal>~/.maven/cache/maven-sdocbook-plugin-1.4/plugin-properties</literal>
       and change the <literal>maven.sdocbook.stylesheets.version</literal> property
       to the version that was actually downloaded.
       </para>
       </note>

      <para>To build a source checkout with Maven:<programlisting>% cd CHECKOUT_DIR 
% $MAVEN_HOME/bin/maven dist</programlisting>In the target/distribution
      subdir, you will find packaged source and binary builds. Run
      $MAVEN_HOME/bin/maven -g for other Maven possibilities.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Running Heritrix</title>

      <para>See the User Manual <xref linkend="heritrix_user_manual" /> for
      how to run the built Heritrix.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="eclipse">
      <title>Eclipse</title>

      <para>The development team uses Eclipse as the development environment.
      This is of course optional, but for those who want to use Eclipse, you
      can, at the head of the source tree, find Eclipse
      <emphasis>.project</emphasis> and <emphasis>.classpath</emphasis>
      configuration files that should make integrating the source checkout into
      your Eclipse development environment straight-forward.</para>

      <para>When running direct from checkout directories, rather than a Maven
      build, be sure to use a JDK installation (so that JSP pages can
      compile). You will probably also want to set the 'heritrix.development'
      property (with the "-Dheritrix.development" VM command-line option) to
      indicate certain files are in their development, rather than deployment,
      locations. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Integration self test</title>

      <para>Run the integration self test on the command line by doing the
      following:<programlisting>% $HERITRIX_HOME/bin/heritrix --selftest</programlisting>This
      will set the crawler going against itself, in particular, the selftest
      webapp. When done, it runs an analysis of the produced arc files and
      logs and dumps a ruling into <filename>heritrix_out.log</filename>. See
      the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/selftest/package-summary.html">org.archive.crawler.selftest</ulink>
      package for more on how the selftest works.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="conventions">
    <title>Coding conventions</title>

    <para>Heritrix baselines on SUN's Code Conventions for the Java
    Programming Language <xref linkend="sun_code_conventions" />. It'd be hard
    not to they say so little. They at least say <ulink
    url="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConventions.doc3.html#313">maximum
    line length of 80 characters</ulink>.</para>

    <para>We also will favor much of what is written in the document, Java
    Programming Style Guidelines <xref
    linkend="programming_style_guidelines" />.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Tightenings on the SUN conventions</title>

      <para>Below are tightenings on the SUN conventions used in
      Heritrix.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>No Tabs</title>

        <para>No tabs in source code. Set your editor to indent with
        spaces.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Indent Width</title>

        <para>Indents are 4 characters wide.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Function/Block Bracket Open on Same Line</title>

        <para>Preference is to have the bracket that opens functions and
        blocks on same line as function declaration or block test rather than
        on a new line of its own. For example:<programlisting>if (true) {
    return true;
}</programlisting>and<programlisting>public void main (String [] args) {
    System.println("Hello world");
}</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>File comment</title>

        <para>Here is the eclipse template we use for the file header
        comment:<programlisting>/* ${type_name}
 * 
 * $$Id: developer_manual.xml 5022 2007-03-23 16:06:32Z stack-sf $$
 * 
 * Created on ${date}
 *
 * Copyright (C) ${year} Internet Archive.
 * 
 * This file is part of the Heritrix web crawler (crawler.archive.org).
 * 
 * Heritrix is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU Lesser Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of the License, or
 * any later version.
 * 
 * Heritrix is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, 
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU Lesser Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser Public License
 * along with Heritrix; if not, write to the Free Software
 * Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
 */
${package_declaration}</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Long versus int</title>

      <para>We will be performing multi-billion resource crawls -- which may
      have to pass up billions of pages that don't make the time/priority cut.
      Our access tools will range over tens if not hundreds of billions of
      resources. We may often archive resources larger than 2GB. Keep these in
      mind when choosing between 'int' (max value: around 2 billion) and
      'long' (max value: around 9 quintillion) in your code.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Unit tests code in same package</title>

      <para>"[A ] popular convention is to place all test classes in a
      parallel directory structure. This allows you to use the same Java
      package names for your tests, while keeping the source files separate.
      To be honest, we do not like this approach because you must look in two
      different directories to find files." from <emphasis>Section 4.11.3,
      Java Extreme Programming Cookbook, By Eric M. Burke, Brian M.
      Coyner</emphasis>. We agree with the above so we put Unit Test classes
      beside the classes they are testing in the source tree giving them the
      name of the Class they are testing with a Test suffix.</para>

      <para>Another advantage is that test classes of the same package can get
      at testee's default access methods and members, something a test in
      another package would not be able to do.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="log_messages">
    <title>Log Message Format</title>
    <para>A suggested format for source code log messages can be found at the
    subversion site, <ulink 
    url="http://subversion.tigris.org/hacking.html#log-messages">Log
    Messages</ulink>.
    </para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="overview">
    <title>Overview of the crawler</title>

    <para>The Heritrix Web Crawler is designed to be modular. Which modules to
    use can be set at runtime from the user interface. Our hope is that if you
    want the crawler to behave different from the default, it should only be a
    matter of writing a new module as a replacement or in addition to the
    modules shipped with the crawler.</para>

    <para>The rest of this document assumes you have a basic understanding of
    how to run a crawl (see: <xref linkend="heritrix_user_manual" />). Since
    the crawler is written in the Java programming language, you also need a
    fairly good understanding of Java.</para>

    <para>The crawler consists of <emphasis>core classes</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>pluggable modules</emphasis>. The core classes can be
    configured, but not replaced. The pluggable classes can be substituted by
    altering the configuration of the crawler. A set of basic pluggable
    classes are shipped with the crawler, but if you have needs not met by
    these classes you could write your own.</para>

    <figure pgwide="0">
      <title>Crawler overview</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="622" fileref="../crawler_overview1.png"
                     scalefit="0" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect2>
      <title>The CrawlController</title>

      <para>The CrawlController collects all the classes which cooperate to
      perform a crawl, provides a high-level interface to the running crawl,
      and executes the "master thread" which doles out URIs from the Frontier
      to the ToeThreads. As the "global context" for a crawl, subcomponents
      will usually reach each other through the CrawlController.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Frontier</title>

      <para>The Frontier is responsible for handing out the next URI to be
      crawled. It is responsible for maintaining politeness, that is making
      sure that no web server is crawled too heavily. After a URI is crawled,
      it is handed back to the Frontier along with any newly discovered URIs
      that the Frontier should schedule for crawling.</para>

      <para>It is the Frontier which keeps the state of the crawl. This
      includes, but is not limited to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>What URIs have been discovered</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What URIs are being processed (fetched)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What URIs have been processed</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Frontier implements the Frontier interface and can be
      replaced by any Frontier that implements this interface. It should be
      noted though that writing a Frontier is not a trivial task.</para>

      <para>The Frontier relies on the behavior of at least the
      following external processors: PreconditionEnforcer, LinksScoper
      and the FrontierScheduler (See below for more each of these
      Processors).  The PreconditionEnforcer makes sure dns and robots
      are checked ahead of any fetching. LinksScoper tests if
      we are interested in a particular URL -- whether the URL is
      'within the crawl scope' and if so, what our level of interest in the
      URL is, the priority with which it should be fetched. The
      FrontierScheduler adds ('schedules') URLs to the Frontier for crawling.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>ToeThreads</title>

      <para>The Heritrix web crawler is multi threaded. Every URI is handled
      by its own thread called a ToeThread. A ToeThread asks the Frontier for
      a new URI, sends it through all the processors and then asks for a new
      URI.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Processors</title>

      <para>Processors are grouped into processor chains (<xref
      linkend="processor_chains" />). Each chain does some processing on a
      URI. When a Processor is finished with a URI the ToeThread sends the URI
      to the next Processor until the URI has been processed by all the
      Processors. A processor has the option of telling the URI to skip to a
      particular chain. Also if a processor throws a fatal error, the
      processing skips to the Post-processing chain.</para>

      <figure id="processor_chains">
        <title>Processor chains</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../processing_steps.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The task performed by the different processing chains are as
      follows:</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Pre-fetch processing chain</title>

        <para>The first chain is responsible for investigating if the URI could
        be crawled at this point. That includes checking if all preconditions
        are met (DNS-lookup, fetching robots.txt, authentication). It is also
        possible to completely block the crawling of URIs that have not passed
        through the scope check.</para>

        <para>In the <literal>Pre-fetch processing</literal> chain the
        following processors should be included (or replacement modules that
        perform similar operations):<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Preselector</emphasis></para>

              <para>Last check if the URI should indeed be crawled. Can for
              example recheck scope. Useful if scope rules have been changed
              after the crawl starts. The scope is usually checked by the
              LinksScoper, before new URIs are added to the Frontier to be
              crawled. If the user changes the scope limits, it will not
              affect already queued URIs. By rechecking the scope at this
              point, you make sure that only URIs that are within current
              scope are being crawled.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis
              role="bold">PreconditionEnforcer</emphasis></para>

              <para>Ensures that all preconditions for crawling a URI have
              been met. These currently include verifying that DNS and
              robots.txt information has been fetched for the URI.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Fetch processing chain</title>

        <para>The processors in this chain are responsible for getting the
        data from the remote server. There should be one processor for each
        protocol that Heritrix supports: e.g. FetchHTTP.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Extractor processing chain</title>

        <para>At this point the content of the document referenced by the URI
        is available and several processors will in turn try to get new links
        from it.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Write/index processing chain</title>

        <para>This chain is responsible for writing the data to archive files.
        Heritrix comes with an ARCWriterProcessor which writes to the ARC
        format. New processors could be written to support other formats and
        even create indexes.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Post-processing chain</title>

        <para>A URI should always pass through this chain even if a decision
        not to crawl the URI was done in a processor earlier in the chain. The
        post-processing chain must contain the following processors (or
        replacement modules that perform similar operations):<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">CrawlStateUpdater</emphasis></para>

              <para>Updates the per-host information that may have been
              affected by the fetch. This is currently robots and IP address
              info.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">LinksScoper</emphasis></para>

              <para>Checks all links extracted from the current download
              against the crawl scope.  Those that are out of scope are
              discarded.  Logging of discarded URLs can be enabled.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">FrontierScheduler</emphasis></para>
                <para>'Schedules' any URLs stored as CandidateURIs found
                in the current CrawlURI with the frontier for crawling.
                Also schedules prerequisites if any.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="settings">
    <title>Settings</title>

    <para>The settings framework is designed to be a flexible way to configure
    a crawl with special treatment for subparts of the web without adding too
    much performance overhead. If you want to write a module which should be
    configurable through the user interface, it is important to have a basic
    understanding of the Settings framework (for the impatient, have a look at
    <xref linkend="chap_modules_common" /> for code examples). At its core the
    settings framework is a way to keep persistent, context sensitive
    configuration settings for any class in the crawler.</para>

    <para>All classes in the crawler that have configurable settings,
    subclass
    <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html">ComplexType</ulink>
    or one of its descendants. The ComplexType implements the
    javax.management.DynamicMBean interface. This gives you a way to ask the
    object for what attributes it supports the standard methods for getting
    and setting these attributes.</para>

    <para>The entry point into the settings framework is the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/SettingsHandler.html">SettingsHandler</ulink>.
    This class is responsible for loading and saving from persistent storage
    and for interconnecting the different parts of the framework.</para>

    <figure id="settings_overview">
      <title>Schematic view of the Settings Framework</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../settings1.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect2>
      <title>Settings hierarchy</title>

      <para>The settings framework supports a hierarchy of settings. This
      hierarchy is built by <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/CrawlerSettings.html">CrawlerSettings</ulink>
      objects. On the top there is a settings object representing the global
      settings. This consists of all the settings that a crawl job needs for
      running. Beneath this global object there is one "per" settings object
      for each host/domain which has settings that should override the order
      for that particular host or domain.</para>

      <para>When the settings framework is asked for an attribute for a
      specific host, it will first try to see if this attribute is set for
      this particular host. If it is, the value will be returned. If not, it
      will go up one level recursively until it eventually reaches the order
      object and returns the global value. If no value is set here either
      (normally it would be), a hard coded default value is returned.</para>

      <para>All per domain/host settings objects only contain those settings
      which are to be overridden for that particular domain/host. The
      convention is to name the top level object "global settings" and the
      objects beneath "per settings" or "overrides" (although the refinements
      described next, also do overriding).</para>

      <para>To further complicate the picture, there is also settings objects
      called refinements. An object of this type belongs to a global or per
      settings object and overrides the settings in its owners object if some
      criteria is met. These criteria could be that the URI in question
      conforms to a regular expression or that the settings are consulted
      at a specific time of day limited by a time span.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>ComplexType hierarchy</title>

      <para>All the configurable modules in the crawler subclasses ComplexType
      or one of its descendants. The ComplexType is responsible for keeping
      the definition of the configurable attributes of the module. The actual
      values are stored in an instance of DataContainer. The DataContainer is
      never accessed directly from user code. Instead the user accesses the
      attributes through methods in the ComplexType. The attributes are
      accessed in different ways depending on
      if it is from the user interface or
      from inside a running crawl.</para>

      <para>When an attribute is accessed from the URI (either reading or
      writing) you want to make sure that you are editing the attribute in the
      right context. When trying to override an attribute, you don't want the
      settings framework to traverse up to an effective value for the attribute,
      but instead want to know that the attribute is not set on this level. To
      achieve this, there is <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getLocalAttribute(org.archive.crawler.settings.CrawlerSettings,%20java.lang.String)">getLocalAttribute(CrawlerSettings
      settings, String name)</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#setAttribute(org.archive.crawler.settings.CrawlerSettings,%20javax.management.Attribute)">setAttribute(CrawlerSettings
      settings, Attribute attribute)</ulink> methods taking a settings object
      as a parameter. These methods works only on the supplied settings
      object. In addition the methods <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getAttribute(java.lang.String)">getAttribute(name)</ulink>
      and <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#setAttribute(javax.management.Attribute)">setAttribute(Attribute
      attribute)</ulink> is there for conformance to the Java JMX
      specification. The latter two always works on the global settings
      object.</para>

      <para>Getting an attribute within a crawl is different in that you
      always want to get a value even if it is not set in its context. That
      means that the settings framework should work its way up the settings
      hierarchy to find the value in effect for the context. The method <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getAttribute(java.lang.String,%20org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">getAttribute(String
      name, CrawlURI uri)</ulink> should be used to make sure that the right
      context is used. The <xref linkend="get_attribute_flow" /> shows how the
      settings framework finds the effective value given a context.</para>

      <figure id="get_attribute_flow">
        <title>Flow of getting an attribute</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../settings2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The different attributes each have a type. The allowed types all
      subclass the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/Type.html">Type</ulink>
      class. There are tree main types:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>SimpleType</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ListType</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ComplexType</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Except for the SimpleType, the actual type used will be a subclass
      of one of these main types.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>SimpleType</title>

        <para>The <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/SimpleType.html">SimpleType</ulink>
        is mainly for representing Java wrappers for the Java primitive
        types. In addition it also handles the 
        <literal>java.util.Date</literal> type and a
        special Heritrix <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/TextField.html">TextField</ulink>
        type. Overrides of a SimpleType must be of the same type as the
        initial default value for the SimpleType.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>ListType</title>

        <para>The <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ListType.html">ListType</ulink>
        is further subclassed into versions for some of the wrapped Java
        primitive types (<ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/DoubleList.html">DoubleList</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/FloatList.html">FloatList</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/IntegerList.html">IntegerList</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/LongList.html">LongList</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/StringList.html">StringList</ulink>).
        A List holds values in the same order as they were added. If an
        attribute of type ListType is overridden, then the complete list of
        values is replaced at the override level.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>ComplexType</title>

        <para>The <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html">ComplexType</ulink>
        is a map of name/value pairs. The values can be any Type including new
        ComplexTypes. The ComplexType is defined abstract and you should use
        one of the subclasses <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/MapType.html">MapType</ulink>
        or <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ModuleType.html">ModuleType</ulink>.
        The MapType allows adding of new name/value pairs at runtime, while
        the ModuleType only allows the name/value pairs that it defines at
        construction time. When overriding the MapType the options are either
        override the value of an already existing attribute or add a new one.
        It is not possible in an override to remove an existing attribute. The
        ModuleType doesn't allow additions in overrides, but the predefined
        attributes' values might be overridden. Since the ModuleType is
        defined at construction time, it is possible to set more restrictions
        on each attribute than in the MapType. Another consequence of
        definition at construction time is that you would normally subclass
        the ModuleType, while the MapType is usable as it is. It is possible
        to restrict the MapType to only allow attributes of a certain type.
        There is also a restriction that MapTypes can not contain nested
        MapTypes.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chap_modules_common">
    <title>Common needs for all configurable modules</title>

    <para>As mentioned earlier all configurable modules in Heritrix subclasses
    ComplexType (or one of its descendants). When you write your own module
    you should inherit from <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ModuleType.html">ModuleType</ulink>
    which is a subclass of ComplexType intended to be subclassed by all
    modules in Heritrix.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Definition of a module</title>

      <para>Heritrix knows how to handle a ComplexType and to get the needed
      information to render the user interface part for it. To make this
      happen your module has to obey some rules.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A module should always implement a constructor taking exactly
          one argument - the name argument (<ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ModuleType.html#ModuleType(java.lang.String)">see
          ModuleType(String name)</ulink>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All attributes you want to be configurable should be defined
          in the constructor of the module.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <sect3>
        <title>The obligatory one argument constructor</title>

        <para>All modules need to have a constructor taking a String argument.
        This string is used to identify the module. In the case where a module
        is of a type that is replacing an existing module of which there could
        only be one, it is important that the same name is being used. In this
        case the constructor might choose to ignore the name string and
        substitute it with a hard coded one. This is for example the case with
        the Frontier. The name of the Frontier should always be the string
        "frontier". For this reason the Frontier interface that all
        Frontiers should implement has a static variable:
        <programlisting>public static final String ATTR_NAME = "frontier";</programlisting> which
        implementations of the Frontier use instead of the string argument
        submitted to the constructor. Here is the part of the default
        Frontiers' constructor that shows how this should be
        done. <programlisting>public Frontier(String name) {
    //The 'name' of all frontiers should be the same (Frontier.ATTR_NAME)
    //therefore we'll ignore the supplied parameter. 
    super(Frontier.ATTR_NAME, "HostQueuesFrontier. Maintains the internal" +
        " state of the crawl. It dictates the order in which URIs" +
        " will be scheduled. \nThis frontier is mostly a breadth-first" +
        " frontier, which refrains from emitting more than one" +
        " CrawlURI of the same \'key\' (host) at once, and respects" +
        " minimum-delay and delay-factor specifications for" +
        " politeness.");</programlisting>
        As shown in this example, the
        constructor must call the superclass's constructor. This example also
        shows how to set the description of a module. The description is used
        by the user interface to guide the user in configuring the crawl. If
        you don't want to set a description (strongly discouraged), the
        ModuleType also has a one argument constructor taking just the
        name.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Defining attributes</title>

        <para>The attributes on a module you want to be configurable must be
        defined in the modules constructor. For this purpose the ComplexType
        has a method <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#addElementToDefinition(org.archive.crawler.settings.Type)">addElementToDefinition(Type
        type)</ulink>. The argument given to this method is a definition of
        the attribute. The <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/Type.html">Type</ulink>
        class is the superclass of all the attribute definitions allowed for a
        ModuleType. Since the ComplexType, which ModuleType inherits, is
        itself a subclass of Type, you can add new ModuleTypes as attributes
        to your module. The Type class implements configuration methods common
        for all Types that defines an attribute on your module. The
        addElementToDefinition method returns the added Type so that it is
        easy to refine the configuration of the Type. Lets look at an example
        (also from the default Frontier) of an attribute
        definition.<programlisting linenumbering="numbered">public final static String ATTR_MAX_OVERALL_BANDWIDTH_USAGE =
        "total-bandwidth-usage-KB-sec";
private final static Integer DEFAULT_MAX_OVERALL_BANDWIDTH_USAGE =
        new Integer(0);
...

Type t;
t = addElementToDefinition(
    new SimpleType(ATTR_MAX_OVERALL_BANDWIDTH_USAGE,
    "The maximum average bandwidth the crawler is allowed to use. " +
    "The actual readspeed is not affected by this setting, it only " +
    "holds back new URIs from being processed when the bandwidth " +
    "usage has been to high.\n0 means no bandwidth limitation.",
    DEFAULT_MAX_OVERALL_BANDWIDTH_USAGE));
t.setOverrideable(false);</programlisting> Here we add an attribute definition
        of the SimpleType (which is a subclass of Type). The SimpleType's
        constructor takes three arguments: name, description and a default
        value. Usually the name and default value are defined as constants
        like here, but this is of course optional. The line
        <command>t.setOverrideable(false);</command> informs the settings
        framework to not allow per overrides on this attribute. For a full
        list of methods for configuring a Type see the <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/Type.html">Type</ulink>
        class.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Accessing attributes</title>

      <para>In most cases when the module needs to access its own attributes,
      a CrawlURI is available. The right way to make sure that all the
      overrides and refinements are considered is then to use the method <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getAttribute(java.lang.String,%20org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">getAttribute(String
      name, CrawlURI uri)</ulink> to get the attribute. Sometimes the context
      you are working in could be defined by other objects than the CrawlURI,
      then use the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getAttribute(java.lang.Object,%20java.lang.String)">getAttribute(Object
      context, String name)</ulink> method to get the value. This method tries
      its best at getting some useful context information out of an object.
      What it does is checking if the context is any kind of URI or a settings
      object. If it can't find anything useful, the global settings are used
      as the context. If you don't have any context at all, which is the case
      in some initialization code, the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/ComplexType.html#getAttribute(java.lang.String)">getAttribute(String
      name)</ulink> could be used.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Putting together a simple module</title>

      <para>From what we learned so far, let's put together a module that
      doesn't do anything useful, but show some of the concepts.</para>

      <programlisting>package myModule;

import java.util.logging.Level;
import java.util.logging.Logger;
import javax.management.AttributeNotFoundException;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.MapType;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.ModuleType;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.RegularExpressionConstraint;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.SimpleType;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.Type;

public class Foo extends ModuleType {
  private static Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("myModule.Foo"); <co
          id="simpleEx_logger" linkends="simpleEx_txt_logger" />

  public Foo(String name) {
    Type mySimpleType1 = new SimpleType(
                "name1", "Description1", new Integer(10)); <co
          id="simpleEx_addSimpleType" linkends="simpleEx_txt_addSimpleType" />
    addElementToDefinition(mySimpleType1);

    Type mySimpleType2 = new SimpleType(
                "name2", "Description2", "defaultValue");
    addElementToDefinition(mySimpleType2);
    mySimpleType2.addConstraint(new RegularExpressionConstraint( <co
          id="simpleEx_addConstraint" linkends="simpleEx_txt_addConstraint" />
                ".*Val.*", Level.WARNING,
                "This field must contain 'Val' as part of the string."));

    Type myMapType = new MapType("name3", "Description3", String.class); <co
          id="simpleEx_addMap" linkends="simpleEx_txt_addMap" />
    addElementToDefinition(myMapType);
  }

  public void getMyTypeValue(CrawlURI curi) {
    try {
      int maxBandwidthKB = ((Integer) getAttribute("name1", curi)).intValue(); <co
          id="simpleEx_getAttribute" linkends="simpleEx_txt_getAttribute" />
    } catch (AttributeNotFoundException e) {
      logger.warning(e.getMessage());
    }
  }

  public void playWithMap(CrawlURI curi) {
    try {
      MapType myMapType = (MapType) getAttribute("name3", curi);
      myMapType.addElement(
              null, new SimpleType("name", "Description", "defaultValue")); <co
          id="simpleEx_addElement" linkends="simpleEx_txt_addElement" />
      myMapType.setAttribute(new Attribute("name", "newValue")); <co
          id="simpleEx_setAttribute" linkends="simpleEx_txt_setAttribute" />
    } catch (Exception e) {
      logger.warning(e.getMessage());
    }
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>This example shows several things:<calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_logger" id="simpleEx_txt_logger">
            <para>One thing that we have not mentioned before is how we do
            general error logging. Heritrix uses the standard Java 1.4 logging
            facility. The convention is to initialize it with the class
            name.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_addSimpleType"
                   id="simpleEx_txt_addSimpleType">
            <para>Here we define and add a SimpleType that takes an Integer as
            the argument and setting it to '10' as the default value.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_addConstraint"
                   id="simpleEx_txt_addConstraint">
            <para>It is possible to add constraints on fields. In addition to
            be constrained to only take strings, this field add a requirement
            that the string should contain 'Val' as part of the string. The
            constraint also has a level and a description. The description is
            used by the user interface to give the user a fairly good
            explanation if the submitted value doesn't fit in with the
            constraint. Three levels are honored. Level.INFO</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Level.INFO</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Values are accepted even if they don't fulfill the
                  constraint's requirement. This is used when you don't want
                  to disallow the value, but warn the user that the value
                  seems to be out of reasonable bounds.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Level.WARNING</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The value must be accepted by the constraint to be
                  valid in crawl jobs, but is legal in profiles even if it
                  doesn't. This is used to be able to put values into a
                  profile that a user should change for every crawl job
                  derived from the profile.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Level.SEVERE</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The value is not allowed whatsoever if it isn't
                  accepted by the constraint.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

            <para>See the <ulink
            url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/settings/Constraint.html">Constraint</ulink>
            class for more information.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_addMap" id="simpleEx_txt_addMap">
            <para>This line defines a MapType allowing only Strings as
            values.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_getAttribute"
                   id="simpleEx_txt_getAttribute">
            <para>An example of how to read an attribute.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_addElement" id="simpleEx_txt_addElement">
            <para>Here we add a new element to the MapType. This element is
            valid for this map because its default value is a String.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="simpleEx_setAttribute"
                   id="simpleEx_txt_setAttribute">
            <para>Now we change the value of the newly added attribute. JMX
            requires that the new value is wrapped in an object of type
            Attribute which holds both the name and the new value.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist></para>

    <note>
      <para>To make your module known to Heritrix, you need to make mention of
      it in the appropriate <filename>src/conf/modules</filename> file: i.e.
      if your module is a Processor, it needs to be mentioned in the 
          <filename>Processor.options</filename> file.
          The options files get built into the Heritrix jar.
      </para>
      <para><quote>A little known fact about Heritrix: When trying to read
modules/Processor.options Heritrix will concatenate any such files it finds
on the classpath.
This means that if you write your own processor and wrap it in a jar you can
simply include in that jar a modules/Processor.options file with just the
one line needed to add your processor. Then simply add the new jar to the
$HERITRIX_HOME/lib directory and you are done. No need to mess with the
Heritrix binaries.  For an example of how this is done, look at the code for
this project: <ulink 
url="http://vefsofnun.bok.hi.is/deduplicator/index.html">deduplicator</ulink>
</quote> [Kristinn Sigurðsson on the mailing list,
<ulink url="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/archive-crawler/message/3281">3281</ulink>].
      </para>
      </note>

      <para>If everything seems ok so far, then we are almost ready to write
      some real modules.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="uri">
    <title>Some notes on the URI classes</title>

    <para>URIs<footnote>
        <para>URI (Uniform Resource Identifiers) defined by <ulink
        url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt">RFC 2396</ulink> is a way of
        identifying resources. The relationship between URI, URL and URN is
        described in the RFC: <citation>"A URI can be further classified as a
        locator, a name, or both. The term "Uniform Resource Locator" (URL)
        refers to the subset of URI that identify resources via a
        representation of their primary access mechanism (e.g., their network
        "location"), rather than identifying the resource by name or by some
        other attribute(s) of that resource. The term "Uniform Resource Name"
        (URN) refers to the subset of URI that are required to remain globally
        unique and persistent even when the resource ceases to exist or
        becomes unavailable."</citation> Although Heritrix uses URIs, only
        URLs are supported at the moment. For more information on naming and
        addressing of resources see: <ulink
        url="http://www.w3.org/Addressing/">Naming and Addressing: URIs, URLs,
        ...</ulink> on w3.org's website.</para>
      </footnote> in Heritrix are represented by several classes. The basic
    building block is <literal>org.archive.datamodel.UURI</literal> which
    subclasses <literal>org.apache.commons.httpclient.URI</literal>. "UURI" is
    an abbrieviation for "Usable URI." This class always normalizes and
    derelativizes URIs -- implying that if a UURI instance is successfully
    created, the represented URI will be, at least on its face, "usable" --
    neither illegal nor including superficial variances which complicate later
    processing. It also provides methods for accessing the different parts of
    the URI.</para>

    <para>We used to base all on <literal>java.net.URI</literal> but because
    of bugs and its strict RFC2396 conformance in the face of a real world
    that acts otherwise, its facility was was subsumed by UURI.</para>

    <para>Two classes wrap the <literal>UURI</literal> in Heritrix:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CandidateURI.html">CandidateURI</ulink></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A URI, discovered or passed-in, that may be scheduled (and
          thus become a CrawlURI). Contains just the fields necessary to
          perform quick in-scope analysis. This class wraps an UURI
          instance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html">CrawlURI</ulink></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Represents a candidate URI and the associated state it
          collects as it is crawled. The CrawlURI is an subclass of
          CandidateURI. It is instances of this class that is fed to the
          processors.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <sect2 id="urischemes">
      <title>Supported Schemes (UnsupportedUriSchemeException)</title>
      <para>A property in <literal>heritrix.properties</literal> 
      named <literal>org.archive.crawler.datamodel.UURIFactory.schemes</literal>
      lists supported schemes.  Any scheme not listed here will cause an
      UnsupportedUriSchemeException which will be reported in
      uri-errors.log with a 'Unsupported scheme' prefix.  If you add a
      fetcher for a scheme, you'll need to add to this list of supported
      schemes (Later, Heritrix can ask its fetchers what schemes are
      supported).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The CrawlURI's Attribute list</title>

      <para>The CrawlURI offers a flexible attribute list which is used to
      keep arbitrary information about the URI while crawling. If you are
      going to write a processor you almost certainly will use the attribute
      list. The attribute list is a key/value-pair list accessed by
      typed accessors/setters.
      By convention the key values are picked from the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CoreAttributeConstants.html">CoreAttributeConstants</ulink>
      interface which all processors implement. If you use other keys than
      those listed in this interface, then you must add the handling of that
      attribute to some other module as well.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The recorder streams</title>

      <para>The crawler wouldn't be of much use if it did not give access to
      the HTTP request and response. For this purpose the CrawlURI has the
      <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#getHttpRecorder()">getHttpRecorder()</ulink>
      <footnote>
          <para>This method will most likely change name see <xref
          linkend="refactor_HTTPRecorder" /> for details.</para>
        </footnote> method. The recorder is referenced by the CrawlURI and
      available to all the processors. See <xref
      linkend="writing_a_processor" /> for an explanation on how to use the
      recorder.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="frontier">
    <title>Writing a Frontier</title>

    <para>As mentioned before, the Frontier is a pluggable module
    responsible for deciding which URI to process next, and when. The Frontier
    is also responsible for keeping track of other aspects of the crawls
    internal state which in turn can be used for logging and reporting. Even
    though the responsibilities of the Frontier might not look overwhelming,
    it is one of the hardest modules to write well. You should really
    investigate if your needs could not be met by the existing Frontier, or
    at least mostly met by subclassing an existing Frontier. With
    these warnings in mind, let's go ahead and create a really simple
    Frontier.</para>

    <para><programlisting>package mypackage;

import java.io.IOException;
import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Iterator;
import java.util.List;
import java.util.Map;

import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CandidateURI;
import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI;
import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.FetchStatusCodes;
import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.UURI;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.CrawlController;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.Frontier;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.FrontierMarker;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.exceptions.FatalConfigurationException;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.exceptions.InvalidFrontierMarkerException;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.ModuleType;


/**
 * A simple Frontier implementation for tutorial purposes
 */
public class MyFrontier extends ModuleType implements Frontier,
        FetchStatusCodes {
    // A list of the discovered URIs that should be crawled.
    List pendingURIs = new ArrayList();
    
    // A list of prerequisites that needs to be met before any other URI is
    // allowed to be crawled, e.g. DNS-lookups
    List prerequisites = new ArrayList();
    
    // A hash of already crawled URIs so that every URI is crawled only once.
    Map alreadyIncluded = new HashMap();
    
    // Reference to the CrawlController.
    CrawlController controller;

    // Flag to note if a URI is being processed.
    boolean uriInProcess = false;
    
    // top-level stats
    long successCount = 0;
    long failedCount = 0;
    long disregardedCount = 0;
    long totalProcessedBytes = 0;

    public MyFrontier(String name) {
        super(Frontier.ATTR_NAME, "A simple frontier.");
    }

    public void initialize(CrawlController controller)
            throws FatalConfigurationException, IOException {
        this.controller = controller;
        
        // Initialize the pending queue with the seeds
        this.controller.getScope().refreshSeeds();
        List seeds = this.controller.getScope().getSeedlist();
        synchronized(seeds) {
            for (Iterator i = seeds.iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
                UURI u = (UURI) i.next();
                CandidateURI caUri = new CandidateURI(u);
                caUri.setSeed();
                schedule(caUri);
            }
        }
    }

    public synchronized CrawlURI next(int timeout) throws InterruptedException {
        if (!uriInProcess &amp;&amp; !isEmpty()) {
            uriInProcess = true;
            CrawlURI curi;
            if (!prerequisites.isEmpty()) {
                curi = CrawlURI.from((CandidateURI) prerequisites.remove(0));
            } else {
                curi = CrawlURI.from((CandidateURI) pendingURIs.remove(0));
            }
            curi.setServer(controller.getServerCache().getServerFor(curi));
            return curi;
        } else {
            wait(timeout);
            return null;
        }
    }

    public boolean isEmpty() {
        return pendingURIs.isEmpty() &amp;&amp; prerequisites.isEmpty();
    }

    public synchronized void schedule(CandidateURI caURI) {
        // Schedule a uri for crawling if it is not already crawled
        if (!alreadyIncluded.containsKey(caURI.getURIString())) {
            if(caURI.needsImmediateScheduling()) {
                prerequisites.add(caURI);
            } else {
                pendingURIs.add(caURI);
            }
            alreadyIncluded.put(caURI.getURIString(), caURI);
        }
    }

    public void batchSchedule(CandidateURI caURI) {
        schedule(caURI);
    }

    public void batchFlush() {
    }

    public synchronized void finished(CrawlURI cURI) {
        uriInProcess = false;
        if (cURI.isSuccess()) {
            successCount++;
            totalProcessedBytes += cURI.getContentSize();
            controller.fireCrawledURISuccessfulEvent(cURI);
            cURI.stripToMinimal();
        } else if (cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_DEFERRED) {
            cURI.processingCleanup();
            alreadyIncluded.remove(cURI.getURIString());
            schedule(cURI);
        } else if (cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_ROBOTS_PRECLUDED
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_OUT_OF_SCOPE
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_BLOCKED_BY_USER
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_TOO_MANY_EMBED_HOPS
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_TOO_MANY_LINK_HOPS
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_DELETED_BY_USER) {
            controller.fireCrawledURIDisregardEvent(cURI);
            disregardedCount++;
            cURI.stripToMinimal();
        } else {
            controller.fireCrawledURIFailureEvent(cURI);
            failedCount++;
            cURI.stripToMinimal();
        }
        cURI.processingCleanup();
    }

    public long discoveredUriCount() {
        return alreadyIncluded.size();
    }

    public long queuedUriCount() {
        return pendingURIs.size() + prerequisites.size();
    }

    public long finishedUriCount() {
        return successCount + failedCount + disregardedCount;
    }

    public long successfullyFetchedCount() {
        return successCount;
    }

    public long failedFetchCount() {
        return failedCount;
    }

    public long disregardedFetchCount() {
        return disregardedCount;
    }

    public long totalBytesWritten() {
        return totalProcessedBytes;
    }

    public String report() {
        return "This frontier does not return a report.";
    }

    public void importRecoverLog(String pathToLog) throws IOException {
        throw new UnsupportedOperationException();
    }

    public FrontierMarker getInitialMarker(String regexpr,
            boolean inCacheOnly) {
        return null;
    }

    public ArrayList getURIsList(FrontierMarker marker, int numberOfMatches,
            boolean verbose) throws InvalidFrontierMarkerException {
        return null;
    }

    public long deleteURIs(String match) {
        return 0;
    }

}</programlisting></para>

    <para><note>
        <para>To test this new Frontier you must add it to the classpath. Then
        to let the user interface be aware of it, you must add the fully
        qualified classname to the 
        <filename>Frontier.options</filename> file in the 
        <literal>conf/modules</literal>
        directory.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para>This Frontier hands out the URIs in the order they are discovered,
    one at a time. To make sure that the web servers are not overloaded it
    waits until a URI is finished processing before it hands out the next one.
    It does not retry URIs for other reasons than prerequisites not met (DNS
    lookup and fetching of robots.txt). This Frontier skips a lot of the tasks
    a real Frontier should take care of. The first thing is that it doesn't
    log anything. A real Frontier would log what happened to every URI. A real
    Frontier would also be aware of the fact that Heritrix is multi threaded
    and try to process as many URIs simultaneously as allowed by the number of
    threads without breaking the politeness rules. Take a look at <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/xref/org/archive/crawler/frontier/BdbFrontier.html">Frontier</ulink>
    <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/frontier/BdbFrontier.html">(javadoc)</ulink>
    to see how a full blown Frontier might look like.</para>

    <para>All Frontiers must implement the Frontier interface. Most
    Frontiers will also implement the FetchStatusCodes because these codes are
    used to determine what to do with a URI after it has returned from the
    processing cycle. In addition you might want to implement the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/event/CrawlStatusListener.html">CrawlStatusListener</ulink>
    which enables the Frontier to be aware of starts, stops, and pausing of a
    crawl. For this simple example we don't care about that. The most
    important methods in the Frontier interface are:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>next(int timeout)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>schedule(CandidateURI caURI)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>finished(CrawlURI cURI)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>The <xref linkend="figure_frontier_sequence" /> shows a
    simplified sequence diagram of the Frontiers collaboration with other
    classes. For readability, the processors (of which there are more than
    showed in this diagram) are chained together in this diagram. It is
    actually the ToeThread that runs each processor in turn.<figure
        id="figure_frontier_sequence">
        <title>Frontier data flow</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../frontier1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>As the diagram shows, the next() method of the Frontier will
    return URI's from the prerequisite list before the pending queue is
    considered. Let's take a closer look at the
    implementation.<programlisting>    public synchronized CrawlURI next(int timeout) throws InterruptedException {
        if (!uriInProcess &amp;&amp; !isEmpty()) { <co
          id="frontierNextEx_inProcess"
          linkends="frontierNextEx_txt_inProcess" />
            uriInProcess = true;
            CrawlURI curi;
            if (!prerequisites.isEmpty()) { <co
          id="frontierNextEx_prerequisite"
          linkends="frontierNextEx_txt_prerequisite" />
                curi = CrawlURI.from((CandidateURI) prerequisites.remove(0));
            } else {
                curi = CrawlURI.from((CandidateURI) pendingURIs.remove(0));
            }
            curi.setServer(controller.getServerCache().getServerFor(curi)); <co
          id="frontierNextEx_setServer"
          linkends="frontierNextEx_txt_setServer" />
            return curi;
        } else {
            wait(timeout); <co id="frontierNextEx_wait"
          linkends="frontierNextEx_txt_wait" />
            return null;
        }
    }</programlisting> <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="frontierNextEx_inProcess"
                 id="frontierNextEx_txt_inProcess">
          <para>First we check if there is a URI in process already, then
          check if there are any URIs left to crawl.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierNextEx_prerequisite"
                 id="frontierNextEx_txt_prerequisite">
          <para>Make sure that we let the prerequisites be processed before
          any regular pending URI. This ensures that DNS-lookups and fetching
          of robots.txt is done before any "real" data is fetched from the
          host. Note that DNS-lookups are treated as an ordinary URI from the
          Frontier's point of view. The next lines pulls a CandidateURI from
          the right list and turn it into a CrawlURI suitable for being
          crawled. The <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#from(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CandidateURI)">CrawlURI.from(CandidateURI)</ulink>
          method is used because the URI in the list might already be a
          CrawlURI and could then be used directly. This is the case for URIs
          where the preconditions was not met. As we will see further down
          these URIs are put back into the pending queue.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierNextEx_setServer"
                 id="frontierNextEx_txt_setServer">
          <para>This line is very important. Before a CrawlURI can be
          processed it must be associated with a CrawlServer. The reason for
          this, among others, is to be able to check preconditions against the
          URI's host (for example so that DNS-lookups are done only once for
          each host, not for every URI).</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierNextEx_wait" id="frontierNextEx_txt_wait">
          <para>In this simple example, we are not being aware of the fact
          that Heritrix is multithreaded. We just let the method wait the
          timeout time and the return null if no URIs where ready. The
          intention of the timeout is that if no URI could be handed out at
          this time, we should wait the timeout before returning null. But if
          a URI becomes available during this time it should wake up from the
          wait and hand it out. See the javadoc for <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Frontier.html#next(int)">next(timeout)</ulink>
          to get an explanation.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist></para>

    <para>When a URI has been sent through the processor chain it ends up in
    the LinksScoper. All URIs should end up here even if the preconditions
    where not met and the fetching, extraction and writing to the archive has
    been postponed. The LinksScoper iterates through all new URIs
    (prerequisites and/or extracted URIs) added to the CrawlURI and, if they
    are within the scope, converts them from Link objects to CandidateURI
    objects.  Later in the postprocessor chain, the FrontierScheduler adds
    them to Frontier by calling the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Frontier.html#schedule(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CandidateURI)">schedule(CandidateURI)</ulink>
    method. There is also a batch version of the schedule method for
    efficiency, see the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Frontier.html">javadoc</ulink>
    for more information. This simple Frontier treats them the
    same.<programlisting>    public synchronized void schedule(CandidateURI caURI) {
        // Schedule a uri for crawling if it is not already crawled
        if (!alreadyIncluded.containsKey(caURI.getURIString())) { <co
          id="frontierScheduleEx_containsKey"
          linkends="frontierScheduleEx_txt_containsKey" />
            if(caURI.needsImmediateScheduling()) { <co
          id="frontierScheduleEx_prerequisite"
          linkends="frontierScheduleEx_txt_prerequisite" />
                prerequisites.add(caURI);
            } else {
                pendingURIs.add(caURI);
            }
            alreadyIncluded.put(caURI.getURIString(), caURI); <co
          id="frontierScheduleEx_addIncluded"
          linkends="frontierScheduleEx_txt_addIncluded" />
        }
    }</programlisting> <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="frontierScheduleEx_containsKey"
                 id="frontierScheduleEx_txt_containsKey">
          <para>This line checks if we already has scheduled this URI for
          crawling. This way no URI is crawled more than once.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierScheduleEx_prerequisite"
                 id="frontierScheduleEx_txt_prerequisite">
          <para>If the URI is marked by a processor as a URI that needs
          immediate scheduling, it is added to the prerequisite queue.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierScheduleEx_addIncluded"
                 id="frontierScheduleEx_txt_addIncluded">
          <para>Add the URI to the list of already scheduled URIs.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist></para>

    <para>After all the processors are finished (including the
    FrontierScheduler's
    scheduling of new URIs), the ToeThread calls the Frontiers <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Frontier.html#finished(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">finished(CrawlURI)</ulink>
    method submitting the CrawlURI that was sent through the
    chain.<programlisting>    public synchronized void finished(CrawlURI cURI) {
        uriInProcess = false;
        if (cURI.isSuccess()) { <co id="frontierFinishedEx_isSuccess"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_isSuccess" />
            successCount++;
            totalProcessedBytes += cURI.getContentSize();
            controller.fireCrawledURISuccessfulEvent(cURI); <co
          id="frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fireEvent" />
            cURI.stripToMinimal(); <co id="frontierFinishedEx_strip"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_strip" />
        } else if (cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_DEFERRED) { <co
          id="frontierFinishedEx_deferred"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_deferred" />
            cURI.processingCleanup(); <co id="frontierFinishedEx_cleanup"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_cleanup" />
            alreadyIncluded.remove(cURI.getURIString());
            schedule(cURI);
        } else if (cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_ROBOTS_PRECLUDED <co
          id="frontierFinishedEx_disregard"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_disregard" />
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_OUT_OF_SCOPE
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_BLOCKED_BY_USER
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_TOO_MANY_EMBED_HOPS
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_TOO_MANY_LINK_HOPS
                || cURI.getFetchStatus() == S_DELETED_BY_USER) {
            controller.fireCrawledURIDisregardEvent(cURI); <co
          id="frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent2"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fireEvent" />
            disregardedCount++;
            cURI.stripToMinimal(); <co id="frontierFinishedEx_strip2"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_strip" />
        } else { <co id="frontierFinishedEx_fail"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fail" />
            controller.fireCrawledURIFailureEvent(cURI); <co
          id="frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent3"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fireEvent" />
            failedCount++;
            cURI.stripToMinimal(); <co id="frontierFinishedEx_strip3"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_strip" />
        }
        cURI.processingCleanup(); <co id="frontierFinishedEx_cleanup2"
          linkends="frontierFinishedEx_txt_cleanup" />
    }</programlisting>The processed URI will have status information attached
    to it. It is the task of the finished method to check these statuses and
    treat the URI according to that (see <xref
    linkend="refactor_frontier_dispositions" />).<calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_isSuccess"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_isSuccess">
          <para>If the URI was successfully crawled we update some counters
          for statistical purposes and "forget about it".</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent2 frontierFinishedEx_fireEvent3"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fireEvent">
          <para>Modules can register with the <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlController.html">controller</ulink>
          to receive <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/event/CrawlURIDispositionListener.html">notifications</ulink>
          when decisions are made on how to handle a CrawlURI. For example the
          <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/admin/StatisticsTracker.html">StatisticsTracker</ulink>
          is dependent on these notifications to report the crawler's
          progress. Different fireEvent methods are called on the controller
          for each of the different actions taken on the CrawlURI.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_strip frontierFinishedEx_strip2 frontierFinishedEx_strip3"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_strip">
          <para>We call the stripToMinimal method so that all data structures
          referenced by the URI are removed. This is done so that any class
          that might want to serialize the URI could be do this as efficient
          as possible.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_deferred"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_deferred">
          <para>If the URI was deferred because of a unsatisfied precondition,
          reschedule it. Also make sure it is removed from the already
          included map.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_cleanup frontierFinishedEx_cleanup2"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_cleanup">
          <para>This method nulls out any state gathered during
          processing.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_disregard"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_disregard">
          <para>If the status is any of the one in this check, we treat it as
          disregarded. That is, the URI could be crawled, but we don't want it
          because it is outside some limit we have defined on the
          crawl.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="frontierFinishedEx_fail"
                 id="frontierFinishedEx_txt_fail">
          <para>If it isn't any of the previous states, then the crawling of
          this URI is regarded as failed. We notify about it and then forget
          it.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="writefilter">
    <title>Writing a Filter</title>

    <para>Filters<footnoteref linkend="footnote_scope_problems" /> are modules
    that take a CrawlURI and determine if it matches the criteria of the
    filter. If so it returns true, otherwise it returns false.</para>

    <para>A filter could be used in several places in the crawler. Most
    notably is the use of filters in the Scope. Aside that, filters are also
    used in processors. Filters applied to processors always filter URIs out.
    That is to say that any URI matching a filter on a processor will
    effectively skip over that processor. This can be useful to disable (for
    instance) link extraction on documents coming from a specific section of a
    given website.</para>

    <para>All Filters should subclass the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Filter.html">Filter</ulink>
    class. Creating a filter is just a matter of implementing the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Filter.html#innerAccepts(java.lang.Object)">innerAccepts(Object)</ulink>
    method. Because of the planned overhaul of the scopes and filters, we will
    not provide a extensive example of how to create a filter at this point.
    It should be pretty easy though to follow the directions in the
    javadoc. For your filter to show in the application interface, you'll need
    to edit <filename>src/conf/modules/Filter.options</filename></para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="scope">
    <title>Writing a Scope</title>

    <para>A <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlScope.html">CrawlScope</ulink>
    <footnote id="footnote_scope_problems">
        <para>It has been identified problems with how the Scopes are defined.
        Please see the user manual for a discussion of the <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/articles/user_manual/config.html#scopeproblems">problems
        with the current Scopes</ulink>. The proposed changes to the Scope
        will affect the Filters as well.</para>
      </footnote> instance defines which URIs are "in" a particular crawl. It
    is essentially a Filter which determines (actually it subclasses the
    <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Filter.html">Filter</ulink>
    class), looking at the totality of information available about a
    CandidateURI/CrawlURI instance, if that URI should be scheduled for
    crawling. Dynamic information inherent in the discovery of the URI, such
    as the path by which it was discovered, may be considered. Dynamic
    information which requires the consultation of external and potentially
    volatile information, such as current robots.txt requests and the history
    of attempts to crawl the same URI, should NOT be considered. Those
    potentially high-latency decisions should be made at another step.</para>

    <para>As with Filters, the scope will be going through a refactoring.
    Because of that we will only briefly describe how to create new Scopes at
    this point.</para>

    <para>All Scopes should subclass the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlScope.html">CrawlScope</ulink>
    class. Instead of overriding the innerAccepts method as you would do if
    you created a filter, the CrawlScope class implements this and instead
    offers several other methods that should be overriden instead. These
    methods acts as different type of filters that the URI will be checked
    against. In addition the CrawlScope class offers a list of exclude filters
    which can be set on every scope. If the URI is accepted (matches the test)
    by any of the filters in the exclude list, it will be considered being out
    of scope. The implementation of the innerAccepts method in the CrawlSope
    is as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>protected final boolean innerAccepts(Object o) {
    return ((isSeed(o) || focusAccepts(o)) || additionalFocusAccepts(o) ||
            transitiveAccepts(o)) &amp;&amp; !excludeAccepts(o);
}</programlisting></para>

    <para>The result is that the checked URI is considered being inside the
    crawl's scope if it is a seed or is accepted by any of the focusAccepts,
    additionalFocusAccepts or transitiveAccepts, unless it is matched by any
    of the exclude filters.</para>

    <para>When writing your own scope the methods you might want to override
    are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlScope.html#focusAccepts(java.lang.Object)">focusAccepts(Object)</ulink>
        the focus filter should rule things in by prima facia/regexp-pattern
        analysis. The typical variants of the focus filter are:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>broad: accept all</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>domain: accept if on same 'domain' (for some definition)
              as seeds</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>host: accept if on exact host as seeds</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>path: accept if on same host and a shared path-prefix as
              seeds</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>Heritrix ships with scopes that implement each of
        these variants. An implementation of a new scope might thus be
        subclassing one of these scopes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlScope.html#additionalFocusAccepts(java.lang.Object)">additionalFocusAccepts(Object)</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/CrawlScope.html#transitiveAccepts(java.lang.Object)">transitiveAccepts(Object)</ulink>
        the transitive filter rule extra items in by dynamic path analysis
        (for example, off site embedded images).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="processor">
    <title id="writing_a_processor">Writing a Processor</title>

    <para>All processors extend <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Processor.html">org.archive.crawler.framework.Processor</ulink>.
    In fact that is a complete class and could be used as a valid processor,
    only it doesn't actually do anything.</para>

    <para>Extending classes need to override the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Processor.html#innerProcess(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">innerProcess(CrawlURI)</ulink>
    method on it to add custom behavior. This method will be invoked for each
    URI being processed and this is therfore where a processor can affect
    it.</para>

    <para>Basically the innerProcess method uses the CrawlURI that is passed
    to it as a parameter (see <xref linkend="editingCURI" />) and the
    underlying HttpRecorder (managed by the ToeThread) (see <xref
    linkend="httprecorder" />) to perform whatever actions are needed.</para>

    <para>Fetchers read the CrawlURI, fetch the relevant document and write to
    the HttpRecorder. Extractors read the HttpRecorder and add the discovered
    URIs to the CrawlURIs list of discovered URIs etc. Not all processors need
    to make use of the HttpRecorder.</para>

    <para>Several other methods can also be optionally overriden for special
    needs:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Processor.html#initialTasks()">initialTasks()</ulink></para>

        <para>This method will be called after the crawl is set up, but before
        any URIs are crawled.</para>

        <para>Basically it is a place to write initialization code that only
        needs to be run once at the start of a crawl.</para>

        <para>Example: The <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/fetcher/FetchHTTP.html">FetchHTTP</ulink>
        processor uses this method to load the cookies file specified in the
        configuration among other things.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Processor.html#innerProcess(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">finalTasks()
        </ulink></para>

        <para>This method will be called after the last URI has been processed
        that will be processed. That is at the very end of a crawl (assuming
        that the crawl terminates normally).</para>

        <para>Basically a place to write finalization code.</para>

        <para>Example: The FetchHTTP processor uses it to save cookies
        gathered during the crawl to a specified file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/Processor.html#innerProcess(org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI)">report()
        </ulink></para>

        <para>This method returns a string that contains a human readable
        report on the status and/or progress of the processor. This report is
        accessible via the WUI and is also written to file at the end of a
        crawl.</para>

        <para>Generally, a processor would include the number of URIs that
        they've handled, the number of links extracted (for link extractors)
        or any other abitrary information of relevance to that
        processor.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="editingCURI">
      <title>Accessing and updating the CrawlURI</title>

      <para>The CrawlURI contains quite a bit of data. For an exhaustive look
      refer to its <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html">Javadoc</ulink>.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#getAList()">getAlist()</ulink></para>

          <para>This method returns the CrawlURI's 'AList'. 
          <note><para><literal>getAlist()</literal> has been deprecated.
          Use the typed accessors/setters instead.</para></note>
          The AList is
          basically a hash map. It is used instead of the Java HashMap or
          Hashtable because it is more efficient (especially when it comes to
          serializing it). It also has typed methods for adding and getting
          strings, longs, dates etc.</para>

          <para>Keys to values and objects placed in it are defined in the
          <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CoreAttributeConstants.html">CoreAttributeConstants</ulink>.</para>

          <para>It is of course possible to add any arbitrary entry to it but
          that requires writing both the module that sets the value and the
          one that reads it. This may in fact be desirable in many cases, but
          where the keys defined in CoreAttributeConstants suffice and fit we
          strongly recommend using them.</para>

          <para>The following is a quick overview of the most used
          CoreAttributeConstants:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">A_CONTENT_TYPE</emphasis></para>

              <para>Extracted MIME type of fetched content; should be set
              immediately by fetching module if possible (rather than waiting
              for a later analyzer)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">LINK COLLECTIONS</emphasis></para>

              <para>There are several Java Collection containing URIs
              extracted from different sources. Each link is a Link
              containing the extracted URI. The URI can be relative. The
              LinksScoper will read this list and convert Links inscope
              to CandidateURIs for adding to the Frontier by
              FrontierScheduler.</para>

              <note>
                <para>CrawlURI has the convenience method <ulink
                url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#addLinkToCollection(java.lang.String,%20java.lang.String)">addLinkToCollection(link,
                collection)</ulink> for adding links to these collections.
                This methods is the prefered way of adding to the
                collections.</para>
              </note>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>A_CSS_LINKS</emphasis></para>

                  <para>URIs extracted from CSS stylesheets</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>A_HTML_EMBEDS</emphasis></para>

                  <para>URIs belived to be embeds.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>A_HTML_LINKS</emphasis></para>

                  <para>Regularly discovered URIs. Despite the name the links
                  could have (in theroy) been found</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>A_HTML_SPECULATIVE_EMBEDS</emphasis></para>

                  <para>URIs discovered via aggressive link extraction. Are
                  treated as embeds but generally with lesser tolerance for
                  nested embeds.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>A_HTTP_HEADER_URIS</emphasis></para>

                  <para>URIs discovered in the returned HTTP header. Usually
                  only redirects.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>See the <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CoreAttributeConstants.html">Javadoc</ulink>
          for CoreAttributeConstants for more.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#setHttpRecorder(org.archive.util.HttpRecorder)">setHttpRecorder(HttpRecorder)</ulink></para>

          <para>Set the HttpRecorder that contains the fetched document. This
          is generally done by the fetching processor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#setHttpRecorder(org.archive.util.HttpRecorder)">getHttpRecorder()</ulink></para>

          <para>A method to get at the fetched document. See <xref
          linkend="httprecorder" /> for more.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#getContentSize()">getContentSize()</ulink></para>

          <para>If a document has been fetched, this method will return its
          size in bytes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html#getContentType()">getContentType()</ulink></para>

          <para>The content (mime) type of the fetched document.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For more see the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlURI.html">Javadoc</ulink>
      for CrawlURI.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="httprecorder">
      <title>The HttpRecorder</title>

      <para>A <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/HttpRecorder.html">HttpRecorder</ulink>
      is attached to each CrawlURI that is successfully fetched by the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/fetcher/FetchHTTP.html">FetchHTTP</ulink>
      processor. Despite its name it could be used for non-http transactions
      if some care is taken. This class will likely be subject to some changes
      in the future to make it more general.</para>

      <para>Basically it pairs together a RecordingInputStream and
      RecordingOutputStream to capture exactly a single HTTP
      transaction.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Writing to HttpRecorder</title>

        <para>Before it can be written to a processor, it must get a reference to
        the current threads HttpRecorder. This is done by invoking the
        HttpRecorder class' static method <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/HttpRecorder.html#getHttpRecorder()">getHttpRecorder()</ulink>.
        This will return the HttpRecorder for the current thread. Fetchers
        should then add a reference to this to the CrawlURI via the method
        discussed above.</para>

        <para>Once a processor has the HttpRecorder object it can access its
        <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/io/RecordingInputStream.html">RecordingInputStream</ulink>
        stream via the <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/HttpRecorder.html#getRecordedInput()">getRecordedInput()</ulink>
        method. The RecordingInputStream extends InputStream and should be
        used to capture the incoming document.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Reading from HttpRecorder</title>

        <para>Processors interested in the contents of the HttpRecorder can
        get at its <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/io/ReplayCharSequence.html">ReplayCharSequence</ulink>
        via its <ulink
        url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/HttpRecorder.html#getReplayCharSequence()">getReplayCharSequence()</ulink>
        method. The ReplayCharSequence is basically a java.lang.CharSequence
        that can be read normally. As discussed above the CrawlURI has a
        method for getting at the existing HttpRecorder.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>An example processor</title>

      <para>The following example is a very simple extractor.</para>

      <programlisting>package org.archive.crawler.extractor;

import java.util.regex.Matcher;

import javax.management.AttributeNotFoundException;

import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CoreAttributeConstants;
import org.archive.crawler.datamodel.CrawlURI;
import org.archive.crawler.framework.Processor;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.SimpleType;
import org.archive.crawler.settings.Type;
import org.archive.crawler.extractor.Link;
import org.archive.util.TextUtils;

/**
 * A very simple extractor. Will assume that any string that matches a 
 * configurable regular expression is a link.
 *
 * @author Kristinn Sigurdsson
 */
public class SimpleExtractor extends Processor
    implements CoreAttributeConstants
{
    public static final String ATTR_REGULAR_EXPRESSION = "input-param";
    public static final String DEFAULT_REGULAR_EXPRESSION = 
        "http://([a-zA-Z0-9]+\\.)+[a-zA-Z0-9]+/"; //Find domains
    
    int numberOfCURIsHandled = 0; 
    int numberOfLinksExtracted = 0;

    public SimpleExtractor(String name) { <co id="simple_1"
          linkends="co_simple_1" />
        super(name, "A very simple link extractor. Doesn't do anything useful.");
        Type e;
        e = addElementToDefinition(new SimpleType(ATTR_REGULAR_EXPRESSION,
            "How deep to look into files for URI strings, in bytes",
            DEFAULT_REGULAR_EXPRESSION));
        e.setExpertSetting(true);
    }

    protected void innerProcess(CrawlURI curi) {

        if (!curi.isHttpTransaction()) <co id="simple_2"
          linkends="co_simple_2" />
        {
            // We only handle HTTP at the moment.
            return;
        }
        
        numberOfCURIsHandled++; <co id="simple_3" linkends="co_simple_3" />

        CharSequence cs = curi.getHttpRecorder().getReplayCharSequence(); <co
          id="simple_4" linkends="co_simple_4" />
        String regexpr = null;
        try {
            regexpr = (String)getAttribute(ATTR_REGULAR_EXPRESSION,curi); <co
          id="simple_5" linkends="co_simple_5" />
        } catch(AttributeNotFoundException e) {
            regexpr = DEFAULT_REGULAR_EXPRESSION;
        }

        Matcher match = TextUtils.getMatcher(regexpr, cs); <co id="simple_6"
          linkends="co_simple_6" />
        
        while (match.find()){ 
            String link = cs.subSequence(match.start(),match.end()).toString(); <co
          id="simple_7" linkends="co_simple_7" />
            curi.createAndAddLink(link, Link.SPECULATIVE_MISC, Link.NAVLINK_HOP);<co id="simple_8"
          linkends="co_simple_8" />
            numberOfLinksExtracted++; <co id="simple_9" linkends="co_simple_9" />
            System.out.println("SimpleExtractor: " + link); <co id="simple_10"
          linkends="co_simple_10" />
        }
        
        TextUtils.recycleMatcher(match); <co id="simple_11"
          linkends="co_simple_11" />
    }

    public String report() { <co id="simple_12" linkends="co_simple_12" />
        StringBuffer ret = new StringBuffer();
        ret.append("Processor: org.archive.crawler.extractor." +
            "SimpleExtractor\n");
        ret.append("  Function:          Example extractor\n");
        ret.append("  CrawlURIs handled: " + numberOfCURIsHandled + "\n");
        ret.append("  Links extracted:   " + numberOfLinksExtracted + "\n\n");

        return ret.toString();
    }
}</programlisting>

      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="simple_1" id="co_simple_1">
          <para>The constructor. As with any Heritrix module it set's up the
          processors name, description and configurable parameters. In this
          case the only configurable parameter is the Regular expression that
          will be used to find links. Both a name and a default value is
          provided for this parameter. It is also marked as an expert
          setting.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_2" id="co_simple_2">
          <para>Check if the URI was fetched via a HTTP transaction. If not it
          is probably a DNS lookup or was not fetched. Either way regular link
          extraction is not possible.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_3" id="co_simple_3">
          <para>If we get this far then we have a URI that the processor will
          try to extract links from. Bump URI counter up by one.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_4" id="co_simple_4">
          <para>Get the ReplayCharSequence. Can apply regular expressions on
          it directly.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_5" id="co_simple_5">
          <para>Look up the regular expression to use. If the attribute is not
          found we'll use the default value.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_6" id="co_simple_6">
          <para>Apply the regular expression. We'll use the <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/TextUtils.html#getMatcher(java.lang.String,%20java.lang.CharSequence)">TextUtils.getMatcher()</ulink>
          utility method for performance reasons.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_7" id="co_simple_7">
          <para>Extract a link discovered by the regular expression from the
          character sequence and store it as a string.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_8" id="co_simple_8">
          <para>Add discovered link to the collection of regular links
          extracted from the current URI.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_9" id="co_simple_9">
          <para>Note that we just discovered another link.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_10" id="co_simple_10">
          <para>This is a handy debug line that will print each extracted link
          to the standard output. You would not want this in production
          code.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_11" id="co_simple_11">
          <para>Free up the matcher object. This too is for performance. See
          the related <ulink
          url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/util/TextUtils.html#freeMatcher(java.util.regex.Matcher)">javadoc</ulink>.</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="simple_12" id="co_simple_12">
          <para>The report states the name of the processor, its function and
          the totals of how many URIs were handled and how many links were
          extracted. A fairly typical report for an extractor.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>

      <para>Even though the example above is fairly simple the processor
      nevertheless works as intended.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Things to keep in mind when writing a processor</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Interruptions</title>

        <para>Classes extending Processor should not trap
        InterruptedExceptions.</para>

        <para>InterruptedExceptions should be allowed to propagate to the
        ToeThread executing the processor.</para>

        <para>Also they should immediately exit their main method
        (<literal>innerProcess()</literal>) if the
        <literal>interrupted</literal> flag is set.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>One processor, many threads</title>

        <para>For each processor only one instance is created per crawl. As
        there are multiple threads running, these processors must be carefully
        written so that no conflicts arise. This usually means that class
        variables can not be used for other things then gathering incremental
        statistics and data.</para>

        <para>There is a facility for having an instance per thread but it has
        not been tested and will not be covered in this document.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="statistics">
    <title>Writing a Statistics Tracker</title>

    <para>A Statistics Tracker is a module that monitors the crawl and records
    statistics of interest to it.</para>

    <para>Statistics Trackers must implement the <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/StatisticsTracking.html">StatisticsTracking
    interface</ulink>. The interface imposes very little on the module.</para>

    <para>Its initialization method provides the new statistics tracker with a
    reference to the CrawlController and thus the module has access to any
    part of the crawl.</para>

    <para>Generally statistics trackers gather information by either querying
    the data exposed by the Frontier or by listening for <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/event/CrawlURIDispositionListener.html">CrawlURI
    disposition events</ulink> and <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/event/CrawlStatusListener.html">crawl
    status events</ulink>.</para>

    <para>The interface extends Runnable. This is based on the assumptions
    that statistics tracker are proactive in gathering their information. The
    CrawlController will start each statistics tracker once the crawl begins.
    If this facility is not needed in a statistics tracker (i.e. all
    information is gathered passively) simply implement the run() method as an
    empty method.<note>
        <para>For new statistics tracking modules to be available in the web
        user interface their class name must be added to the
        <filename>StatisticsTracking.options</filename>
        file under the conf/modules directory. The classes' full name (with
        package info) should be written in its own line, followed by a '|' and
        a descriptive name (containing only [a-z,A-Z]).</para>
      </note></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>AbstractTracker</title>

      <para>A partial implementation of a StatisticsTracker is provided in the
      frameworks package. The <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/framework/AbstractTracker.html">AbstractTracker</ulink>
      implements the StatisticsTracking interface and adds the needed
      infrastructure for doing snapshots of the crawler status.</para>

      <para>This is done implementing the thread aspects of the statistics
      tracker. This means that classes extending the AbstractTracker need not
      worry about thread handling, implementing the logActivity() method
      allows them to poll any information at fixed intervals.</para>

      <para>AbstractTracker also listens for crawl status events and pauses
      and stops its activity based on them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Provided StatisticsTracker</title>

      <para>The admin package contains the only provided implementation of the
      statistics tracking interface. The <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/admin/StatisticsTracker.html">StatisticsTracker</ulink>
      is designed to write progress information to the progress-statistics.log
      as well as providing the web user interface with information about
      ongoing and completed crawls. It also dumps various reports at the end
      of each crawl.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="arcs">
    <title>Internet Archive ARC files</title>

    <para>By default, heritrix writes all its crawled to disk using <ulink
    url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/writer/ARCWriterProcessor.html">ARCWriterProcessor</ulink>.
    This processor writes the found crawl content as Internet Archive ARC
    files. The ARC file format is described here: <ulink
    url="http://www.archive.org/web/researcher/ArcFileFormat.php">Arc File
    Format</ulink>. Heritrix writes version 1 ARC files.</para>

    <para>By default, Heritrix writes <emphasis>compressed</emphasis>
    version 1 ARC files.  The compression is done with gzip, but rather
    compress the ARC as a whole, instead, each ARC Record is in turn
    gzipped.  All gzipped records are concatenated together to make up
    a file of multiple gzipped members.  This concatenation, it turns out,
    is a legal gzip file; you can give it to gzip and it will undo each
    compressed record in turn.  Its an amenable compression technique
    because it allows random seek to a single record and the undoing of
    that record only. Otherwise, first the total ARC would have to be
    uncompressed to get any one record.
    </para>

    <para>Pre-release of Heritrix 1.0, an amendment was made to the ARC file
    version 1 format to allow writing of extra metadata into first record of
    an ARC file. This extra metadata is written as XML. The XML Schema used by
    metadata instance documents can be found at <ulink
    url="http://archive.org/arc/1.0/arc.xsd">http://archive.org/arc/1.0/xsd</ulink>.
    The schema is documented <ulink
    url="http://archive.org/arc/1.0/arc.html">here</ulink>.</para>

    <para>If the extra XML metadata info is present, the second
    '&lt;reserved&gt;' field of the second line of version 1 ARC files will be
    changed from '0' to '1': i.e. ARCs with XML metadata are version
    '1.1'.</para>

    <para>If present, the ARC file metadata record body will contain at least
    the following fields (Later revisions to the ARC may add other
    fields):<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Software and software version used creating the ARC file.
          Example: 'heritrix 0.7.1 http://crawler.archive.org'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The IP of the host that created the ARC file. Example:
          '103.1.0.3'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The hostname of the host that created the ARC file. Example:
          'debord.archive.org'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Contact name of the crawl operator. Default value is
          'admin'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The http-header 'user-agent' field from the crawl-job order
          file. This field is recorded here in the metadata only until the day
          ARCs record the HTTP request made. Example: 'os-heritrix/0.7.0
          (+http://localhost.localdomain)'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The http-header 'from' from the crawl-job order file. This
          field is recorded here in the metadata only until the day ARCs
          record the HTTP request made. Example:
          'webmaster@localhost.localdomain'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The 'description' from the crawl-job order file. Example:
          'Heritrix integrated selftest'</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Robots honoring policy. Example: 'classic'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Organization on whose behalf the operator is running the
          crawl. Example 'Internet Archive'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The recipient of the crawl ARC resource if known. Example:
          'Library of Congress'.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="arcnaming">
      <title>ARC File Naming</title>

      <para>When heritrix creates ARC files, it uses the following template
      naming them: <programlisting>
        &lt;OPERATOR SPECIFIED&gt; '-' &lt;12 DIGIT TIMESTAMP&gt; '-' &lt;SERIAL NO.&gt; '-' &lt;FQDN HOSTNAME&gt; '.arc' | '.gz'
        </programlisting>... where &lt;OPERATOR SPECIFIED&gt; is any operator
      specified text, &lt;SERIAL NO&gt; is a zero-padded 5 digit number and
      &lt;FQDN HOSTNAME&gt; is the fully-qualified domainname on which the
      crawl was run.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="arcreader">
      <title>Reading arc files</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/io/arc/ARCReader.html">ARCReader</ulink>
      can be used reading arc files. It has a command line interface that can
      be used to print out meta info in a pseudo 
      <ulink url="http://www.archive.org/web/researcher/example_cdx.php">CDX
      format</ulink> 
      and for doing random access getting of
      arc records (The command-line interface is described in the <ulink
      url="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/io/arc/ARCReader.html#main(java.lang.String[])">main
      method javadoc</ulink> comments).</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://netarchive.dk/website/sources/index-en.php">Netarchive.dk</ulink>
      have also developed arc reading and writing tools.</para>

      <para>Tom Emerson of Basis Technology has put up a project on
      sourceforge to host a BSD-Licensed C++ ARC reader called <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/libarc/">libarc</ulink> (Its since
      been moved to
      <ulink url="http://archive-access.sourceforge.net/">archive-access</ulink>).</para>

      <para>The French National Library (BnF) has also released a GPL perl/c
      ARC Reader. See 
      <ulink url="http://crawler.archive.org/cgi-bin/wiki.pl?BnfArcTools">BAT</ulink> for documentation and where to download..
      </para>
      See <ulink url="http://archive-access.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/archive-access/archive-access/projects/hedaern/">Hedaern</ulink> for python readers/writers and
      for a skeleton webapp that allows querying by timestamp+date as well
          as full-text search of ARC content..
      <para>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="arcwriter">
      <title>Writing arc files</title>

      <para>Here is an example arc writer application: <ulink
      url="http://nwatoolset.sourceforge.net/docs/NedlibToARC/">Nedlib To ARC
      conversion</ulink>. It rewrites <ulink
      url="http://www.csc.fi/sovellus/nedlib/index.phtml.en">nedlib</ulink>
      files as arcs.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="searching_arcs">
        <title>Searching ARCS</title>
        <para>Check out the <ulink url="http://archive-access.sourceforge.net/projects/nutch/">NutchWAX</ulink>+<ulink
        url="http://archive-access.sourceforge.net/projects/wera/">WERA</ulink> bundle.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <appendix id="futures">
    <title>Future changes in the API</title>

    <para>This appendix lists issues in the API that needs investigation and
    eventually changes to be made. Read this so that you could avoid locking
    yourself to dependencies that is likely to change.</para>

    <sect1 id="refactor_HTTPRecorder">
      <title>The org.archive.util.HTTPRecorder class</title>

      <para>The intention is to allow Heritrix to handle all relevant
      protocols, not only http/https. The naming of HTTPRecorder indicates
      that it is only for HTTP. Hopefully it is not. We have not investigated
      it fully yet, but it might be that changing the name of the class is all
      there is to be done.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="refactor_frontier_dispositions">
      <title>The Frontiers handling of dispositions</title>

      <para>When the Frontier decides which URIs should be treated as deferred
      and which has failed, it must check the fetch status and have knowledge
      about every possible status code. This complicates adding new status
      codes. It should be possible to constrain the number of status groups
      the Frontier has to know and then let the processors decide which group
      a new status code falls into. Possible status groups are:</para>

      <para>successful</para>

      <para>failure</para>

      <para>disregard</para>

      <para>retry immediately</para>

      <para>retry after any prerequisite</para>

      <para>retry at some later time</para>
    </sect1>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="release_numbering">
    <title>Version and Release Numbering</title>

    <para>Heritrix uses a version numbering scheme modeled after the one used
    for Linux kernels. Versions are 3 numbers:</para>

    <para>[major ] .[minor/mode ] .[patchlevel ]</para>

    <para>The major version number, currently at one, increments upon
    significant architectural changes or the achievement of important
    milestones in capabilities. The minor/mode version number increments as
    progress is made within a major version, with the added constraint that
    all external releases have an even minor/mode version number, and all
    internal/development versions have an odd minor/mode version
    number.</para>

    <para>The patchlevel number increments for small sets of changes,
    providing the most fine-grain time line of software evolution. Patchlevels
    increment regularly for internal/development (odd minor level) work, but
    only increment for external releases when an official update to the
    previous release version has been tested and packaged.</para>

    <para>Version numbers are applied as tags of the form
    "heritrix-#_#_#".  Branches occur at major transitions and are labeled
    with the form "heritrix_#_#'.</para> 

    <para>When a particular development-version is thought
    appropriate to become an external/"st able" release, it is considered a
    "Release Candidate" (No where is this written in versions). If testing
    confirms it is suitable for release, it is
    assigned the next even minor/mode value (and a zero patchlevel), 
    version-labelled, and packaged for release. Immediately after release, and
    before additional coding occurs, the HEAD is assigned the next odd
    minor/mode value (and a zero patchlevel) in project/source files.</para>

    <para>If patches are required to a released version, before the next
    release is ready, they are applied to a branch from the release
    version tag, tested, and released as the subsequent patchlevel.</para>

    <para>Keep in mind that each version number is an integer, not merely a
    decimal digit. To use an extreme example: development version 2.99.99
    would be followed by either the 2.99.100 development version patchlevel or
    the 2.100.0 release. (And after such a release, the next development
    version would be 2.101.0.)</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="release">
    <title>Making a Heritrix Release</title>

    <para>Before initiating a release, its assumed that the current HEAD
    or BRANCH version has been run through the integration self test, 
    that all unit tests pass, that the embryonic 
    <ulink url="http://crawler.archive.org/cgi-bin/wiki.pl?CrawlTestPlan">test
    plan</ulink> has been exercised,
    and that general usage shows HEAD -- or BRANCH -- to be release
    worthy.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Send a mail to the list to freeze commits until the all-clear is
        given.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Up the project.xml 'currentVersion' element value (See
        <ulink url="#release_numbering">Version and Release Numbering</ulink>
        for guidance on what version number to use)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update releasenotes.xml bugs and RFEs closed since last
        release (Looking at source code history to figure what's changed is too
        hard; All major changes should have associated BUG and RFE).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Add news of the new release to the site main home page.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Generate the site. Review all documentation making sure it
        remains applicable. Fix at least the embarrassing. Make issues to have
        all that remains addressed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update the README.txt (We used to include in README text-only version
        of dependencies list, release notes including items fixed but now we just
        point to the pertintent html).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Commit all changes made above all in the one commit with a log
        message about new release. Commit files with the new version, the
        README.txt, home page, and all changes in documentation including the changelog
        additions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Wait on a cruisecontrol successful build of all just committed.
        Download the src and binary latest builds from under the cruisecontrol
        'build artifacts' link.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Build the cruisecontrol produced src distribution
        version.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Run both the binary and src-built product through the
        integration self test suite: % $HERITRIX_HOME/bin/heritrix
        --selftest</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tag the repository.  If a bugfix release -- an
        increase in the least significant digits -- then tag the 
        release. Otherwise, if a major or minor release make a branch
        (See <xref linkend="release_numbering" /> for more on release
        versioning).
        Tags should be named for the release name as in if the release
        is 1.10.2, then the tag should be heritrix-1_10_2 (You can't use
        dots in tag names).  If a branch, then name the branch for the
        minor (or major) version name as in, 
        if making a release 1.10.0, then name the branch heritrix-1_10
            and if making 2.0.0, name the branch heritrix-2. 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update the project.xml 'currentVersion' and build.xml 'version'
        property to both be a version number beyond that of the release
        currently being made (If we're releasing 0.2.0, then increment to
        0.3.0).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Login and upload the maven 'dist' product to sourceforge into
        the admin-&gt;File releases section.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Send announcement to mailinglist -- and give an all-clear that
        commits may resume -- and update our release state on freshmeat site
        (Here is the URL I used creating our freshmeat project:
        http://freshmeat.net/add-project/all-done/43820/46804/ -- 46804 is our
        project ID).</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="schema">
    <title>Settings XML Schema</title>
    <para>The XML Schema that describes the crawler job order file can be
    viewed as xhtml here, <ulink
    url="https://archive-crawler.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/archive-crawler/trunk/heritrix/src/webapps/admin/heritrix_settings.html">heritrix_settings.html</ulink>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="profiling">
    <title>Profiling Heritrix</title>
    <para>Heritrix uses <ulink url="http://www.ej-technologies.com/products/jprofiler/overview.html">JProfiler</ulink>.
    See <ulink 
    url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1002336&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539102">[ 1002336 ] Figure what profiler to use</ulink> for
    a (rambling) log of experience with the various profilers and of 
    how we arrived at this choice.
    </para>
  </appendix>

  <bibliography id="biblio">
    <biblioentry id="heritrix_user_manual">
      <abbrev>Heritrix User Guide</abbrev>

      <title><ulink url="http://crawler.archive.org/user.html">Heritrix User
      Guide</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername><ulink url="http://www.archive.org">Internet
        Archive</ulink></publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry id="sun_code_conventions">
      <abbrev>Sun Code Conventions</abbrev>

      <title><ulink
      url="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Code
      Conventions for the Java Programming Language</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry id="programming_style_guidelines">
      <abbrev>Java Programming Style Guidelines</abbrev>

      <title><ulink url="http://geosoft.no/javastyle.html">Java Programming
      Style Guidelines</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername>Geotechnical Software Services</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>Towards web-scale web archeology</abbrev>

      <title><ulink
      url="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/leung01towards.html">Towards web-scale
      web archeology. Research Report 174</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername>Compaq Systems Research Center, Palo Alto,
        CA</publishername>
      </publisher>

      <date>September 10, 2001</date>

      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>S.</firstname>

          <surname>Leung</surname>
        </author>

        <author>
          <firstname>S.</firstname>

          <surname>Perl</surname>
        </author>

        <author>
          <firstname>R.</firstname>

          <surname>Stata</surname>
        </author>

        <author>
          <firstname>J.</firstname>

          <surname>Wiener</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>On High-Performance Web Crawling.</abbrev>

      <title><ulink
      url="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/najork01highperformance.html">On
      High-Performance Web Crawling. Research Report 173</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername>Compaq Systems Research Center, Palo Alto,
        CA</publishername>
      </publisher>

      <date>September 26, 2001</date>

      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Marc</firstname>

          <surname>Najork</surname>
        </author>

        <author>
          <firstname>Allan</firstname>

          <surname>Heydon</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>Mercator: A Scalable, Extensible Web Crawler</abbrev>

      <title><ulink
      url="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/heydon99mercator.html">Mercator: A
      Scalable, Extensible Web Crawler</ulink></title>

      <publisher>
        <publishername>Compaq Systems Research Center, Palo Alto,
        CA</publishername>
      </publisher>

      <date>1999</date>

      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Marc</firstname>

          <surname>Najork</surname>
        </author>

        <author>
          <firstname>Allan</firstname>

          <surname>Heydon</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
</article>
